Hi ladies. So this is a recording of a call that we did recently, which is Conf
idence
on Webcap. So we did do this call as a live call, which I would always
recommend that
you try to come to the live calls if you can, because it's just so much better
to talk about
these things when you're with your fellow members, and you can sort of bounce
off each
other, offer each other ideas and insights, and just chat about, you know, what
's happening
for you. So please, please come and use the community wherever you can. But for
those
that couldn't make it to this call, this is just a quick whistle stop. Whistle
stop
tour, really, of the call that we did. I'm just going to run through the slides
with
you to have a look at our home. Okay. So this call is just a short call. That
is an opportunity
for you to think about what confidence is for you, how you can work it to
enhance your
experience on cam and in the world. So how you can work on your confidence to
feel much
better in your everyday life and on cam. So a quick reflection to start. And I
wonder
if it would be great, by the way, if you had a pen and paper, so maybe you just
need to
pause this video and just get a little pen and paper ready for this call. And
the first
thing I'd like you to reflect on is just what three words sum up, what it feels
like to
be confident. So what does a confident you feel like? What three words might
summarize
what you might feel like when you're feeling confident? You know, I think maybe
my three
words would be competent, calm, curious, maybe. Those are things that I feel
wonderful, confident,
but it might look different to you. So just taking a few moments, maybe just
pause this
video for a sec and think about what three words sum up, what a confident you
feels like.
And we're going to talk just a little bit about understanding low confidence
now. So
let's look at some of the things that influence and shape our confidence. So as
we talk through
this list with your pen and paper, you can write down or you can just think
about how
each aspect has impacted your confidence either in a positive or a negative way
. So we're thinking
about just some of the things in our lives, some of our experiences and
influences that
affect our confidence. And as I say, it can be in a positive or a negative way.
So family
and friends expectations. So what do you think about your family and friends
expectations?
Have they enabled you to feel more confident? Have they been difficult to live
up to? Have
you been made to feel by the people around you in your life that you can be
confident
in yourself, in your abilities, in your appearance? How have your family and
friends expectations
affected your confidence and made you feel? And then school and workplace
culture. So
throughout school, what was it like for you in schools? Is it a place that made
you feel
confident that instilled you with confidence in yourself or not? And thinking
about work,
you know, or maybe university or work? What jobs have you done? And how have
they impacted
your confidence? It could be because of the people that are around you in those
scenarios.
It could be because of the way things work. It could be because of the stigma
and shame
around different jobs. I know that I've had a lot of stigma and shame around
jobs that
have done in the past. And I've also had jobs that have filled me with
confidence. TV and
media. So what do you think about the things that you've watched and listened
to and seen
on social media, like trends that you see over the years? How do you think
those have
impacted your confidence? Culture. So this can be culture as in, you know, if
you're from
a different cultural background or it can just be like UK, British culture. It
can be
the culture, queer culture, for example, you know, my sort of friendships and
social
life is within queer culture, which makes me feel really confident and seen and
great
in my social interactions. But there are different cultures I've been a part of
. I haven't felt
that way for me. And then patriarchy and social stigma. So systems of
oppression, sexism, things
like that, how have they impacted the way that you feel about yourself and how
confident
you can be in yourself? It's really good at exercise just to think about what
are some
of the influences on how you feel about yourself. So as a result of looking
through those aspects
on that list, are there any old stories, narratives or relationships that
continue to impact your
confidence? So this could be in a positive or a negative way. So thinking about
the people
that are around you on a day to day basis, how they speak to you, how you
interact with
them, what your dynamic is with them, any stories that you hold in your mind
about who you are,
you know, I know a lot of people, you know, sort of compare themselves or don't
feel good compared
to other people. Are there any narratives that you have? I'm not good at this
or this part of
me isn't good or I don't look good or whatever it is. Are there any old
narratives that continue
to give you, make you feel impact your confidence, make you feel bad about
yourself or good?
And this is an interesting one. How might your critical thoughts be trying to
protect you?
So there are certain psychological theories that think about how you're you're
in a critic.
So your inner critic is often something, you know, a part of you that kind of
puts you down
that holds some of these old stories and narratives about yourself. It might be
that
and you were always told at school that you were always doing the wrong thing
or your grades were
never good and that made you feel like you weren't an intelligent person or you
had a parent that
always commented on your weight or something like that and then you develop
this inner critical
voice that tells you some of these stories, some of these narratives that you
've been given by other
people. And what we know is that when we're growing up around certain
narratives and we're treated
a certain way and had something affirmed to us over and over again, like you're
not good at such and
such or you're not good at socializing or you don't fit in or whatever it is,
then you can create an
internal voice. So instead of other people having to tell you that, you can
create an internal voice
that then tells you that. And how what happens is that sort of punishes you
first so that the
people can't punish you or comment on you. It can give you a sense of control.
So it doesn't matter
if other people think that about me because I think about me anyway. Or it can
it can
be saying these you can have this inner critic which is saying these things to
you. So in the
hope that you're going to work harder, be better, try harder, change yourself
so that then you're not
going to be shamed or judged or outcast or rejected by other people. So that's
some of the ways that
you're in a critic could be trying to protect you. And it can be really helpful
to think about, okay,
do I have an inner critic? Where did that voice originate from? Who were the
first people to tell
me what this inner critic is telling me? Where did I get these ideas from? And
how might it be
trying to protect me now? Is it still trying to stop other people from judging
me? Is it still
trying to make me better so that I'm acceptable or lovable? And can you extend
some compassion
towards this part of you? This part of you that's trying to avoid shame or
judgment or rejection
or whatever it is, that can be the real huge first step towards feeling more
confident is really
understanding and feeling some compassion for the parts of you that don't feel
confident and that
are, you know, criticizing you inside. Because once you understand what they're
doing for you,
it can be a lot easier not to get dragged in by them. And thirdly, when you're
not feeling
confident, what could you do to return to a more grounded place? So for
instance, if an inner critic,
if you start feeling something, thinking something about yourself that's
negative, what could you do
to return to a more grounded and realistic place? Maybe it's speaking to a
friend, maybe it's listening
to a song that you like, maybe it's using touch, you know, with with yourself
or other grounding
techniques, maybe it's breathing, maybe it's, you know, taking yourself to a
safe place in your mind
to a place that makes you feel calm, a bit of meditative sort of stuff. Maybe
it's just dancing
around and shaking. There's lots of different things. So when you're not
feeling confident,
what could you do to return to a more confident grounded place?
And then cam, let's think about cam specifically. So what can we do to increase
our confidence
on cam? So there's a few ideas here and I'd love it if you shared any ideas
that you might have
in the group in the WhatsApp. We had some people share some ideas on this call.
Music and atmosphere. So personally for me, if I was, you know, anytime I've
been getting on
cam, it's to put on some music and just change, you know, it changes my energy.
If I'm getting ready
for cam, I might put on a certain playlist or certain track so that it gets me
into my power
and I start to feel good about myself and just brush off the stresses of the
day as well, you know.
So music, is that something that could be helpful?
The second one is framing. So, framing means that when it and it can be, this
can be about cam,
but it can be about anything that you do in your life. When we frame something,
we do certain actions
beforehand and we do certain actions afterwards. So it's just a way of being
really intentional
in whatever you're doing. So for instance, if I was to go on a date, for
example, my framing
might be that I sit down with myself and just think about what my intentions
are beforehand,
have a little look in the mirror and just, you know, tell myself that it's okay
, that I'm sort of
just wanting to connect with this person and I'm not going to judge myself and
I'm not going
to take on anything that I don't need to take on. So that might be my framing
action beforehand.
And then afterwards, it might be, you know, phone a friend or have a nice bath
or whatever it is
this. So your body, your mind and body knows, this is the start of my
experience. I'm being
intentional about it and this is what I want for it. And this is the end of my
experience. The date
has ended or the camera session has ended or whatever it is has ended and I'm
coming back to myself.
So framing is about rituals. It helps your body and your mind to feel safe. And
it helps you to
know that you are autonomous, you have control, you are being intentional with
what you're doing.
So you go into something with a set of intentions or, you know, knowing
yourself and looking after
yourself and you come out of something, again, thinking about the experience
and doing things
that make you know that you're coming back to yourself and that experience has
finished.
Self kindness and boundaries. So we talk about boundaries all the time and
loads of our calls have talked about boundaries on camp because that's
something that's missing
in many webcam agencies, you know, as part of what it means to be the ethical
camp communities to
talk about women understanding their boundaries and models understanding their
boundaries.
And we can't understand our boundaries and even begin to implement them without
being kind to
ourselves. So the very, very basics of boundaries is that we have to be able to
be kind to ourselves
and that means not punishing yourself. It means, you know, think of somebody
that you love and trust.
Hopefully there's one person or even pets in your life that you love and trust.
Well, that's how
how you treat them is how you should be treating yourself. You should be
someone that you love and
trust. So offering kindness towards yourself can help you to think about some
boundaries.
Now boundaries are thinking about what is okay for you, what feels safe and
okay and acceptable
for you and what doesn't. So in order to, and so there's, it's one thing
knowing your boundaries.
So you can sit down and maybe write a little list, maybe about cam, what is it
that I'm okay to do,
how do I want to feel on cam, how do I want to be spoken to, how do I not want
to be spoken to,
what do I not want to do. And it doesn't have to be extremely black and white
because we all know
that if you're speaking to one person, one client, you might feel completely
differently
speaking to the next one based on how they show up and how they make you feel,
whether you feel
respected and listened to and autonomous and all the nice things. So they don't
need to be black
and white, your boundaries, but just sitting down and thinking about the kinds
of things that you
know that you're okay with, the kinds of things you're maybe depending on the
person and the kinds
of things you definitely do not want to do. And then there's implementing your
boundaries,
which is the really important step that some people never get to, because we
talk so much about
boundaries in everyday life, but we don't talk about how to implement them and
how to stick to
our boundaries. So once you've written down the kind of things you're okay to
do and the kind of
things you're not okay to do, what the next step in implementing your
boundaries is to think to
yourself and maybe to write down what happens when firstly, how do I know a but
one of my boundaries
has been crossed or is about to be crossed. And usually that's because you're
getting towards
something you know you're not okay with. Your body's giving you signals that
you don't feel good,
you don't feel safe, you don't feel all right, you feel a bit out of control or
that you're not
enjoying what's happening. So noticing when you're coming towards a boundary
and the really important
part of boundary setting is understanding what action you're going to take if
something has either
crossed a boundary or is getting close to crossing a boundary for you. So for
example, if you don't
feel comfortable with a certain topic on can, if a client is you're engaging
with them and you're
you know having a great camp session and then they go towards talking about
this topic,
you can notice okay that's something I don't enjoy talking about, you can
express to them
okay that's not something that uncomfortable we're talking about. So you know
you're getting close
to a boundary and you've done something about it. The other person can then
carry on to perhaps
they'll listen to you and that's great you can carry on, talk about something
else,
perhaps they won't and perhaps they'll continue doing the thing that is
crossing your boundary.
Just like in real life people cross our boundaries even when we've told them
about our boundaries.
So the really important final step in boundaries and this can really help
increase your confidence
overall is that you will on them, you will act on your boundaries being crossed
. So boundary is
not about what you expect of someone else. Boundary is about what is safe for
me and what isn't and
what do I do if it's no longer safe? What do I do if someone crosses a boundary
? Just like if you
have you know a boundary with a family member or I don't talk about this
personal thing because
I don't want to. If they continue to do it then you then have to, you then have
to change your
behaviour, you then have to implement your boundary which means which might look
like
I'm actually I'm not going to continue this conversation because you've crossed
the boundary
there or I'm not going to come to that family gathering anymore because you
keep going on this
subject. So your boundary is you adjusting your behaviour if somebody crosses
your boundary really
important and that can really help you to feel confident when you're going on
cam. When you know
if somebody gets close to crossing a boundary I can question it and if they
then cross the boundary
I will disengage. You know I will say no maybe I'll just close the laptop,
maybe I'll log off.
Whatever it is you need to do to implement your boundary and that can really
help you to
feel confident when you know that you've got full agency over your experience
on cam.
So another thing to increase your confidence on cam is to play to your
strengths and your own
pleasures and as we always say in the ECC you don't need to be just this one-
size-fits-all
version of a model, a webcam model. You can be you and actually the people that
will
become your regulars and enjoy and want to spend extended time with you. We
usually do so because
they're enjoying your energy, they're enjoying you individually and they can
tell that you're
enjoying yourself too. So playing to your strengths and your own pleasures even
if that's just like
talking about things that you like. You know talking about how much you've got
or just incorporating
your own interests into some sexy talk you know. It can really help you to just
feel confident
because then the person's leaning in and sort of really enjoying what you're
bringing but you're
also enjoying it too. Grounding habits, so I guess framing like I was talking
about and rituals can
be really good grounding habits. When your body, when your nervous system, no
your nervous system
is calmed by repetition. So for instance if you're going on cam and you know
you might decide to
have a little ritual before you go on cam. So it might look like framing like I
talked about
being intentional or it might look like other little grounding habits that can
help your nervous
system to understand what's going to happen and just create some consistency
for your body.
So it might be just like lighting a couple of candles or or just changing the
lighting in the
atmosphere. You might use, I mean some people like to sort of use crystals or
different ways of
just just setting up the space and grounding yourself. So again you're being
just intentional
about your experience and you're not just getting swept up and outpacing
yourself and stressing and
rushing and bullying yourself or you know all these things, pacing, slowing
down and
putting some rituals into your cam routine and just coming from a grounded
position at least
when you're starting going on cam. And then a big one, don't compare, connect.
So one of the
reasons for the Ethical Cam Community is that you have a community at your
fingertips that is there
to connect with you and support you. Whenever you're feeling a bit rubbish,
maybe you're
comparing yourself to other people, everybody is different and everybody has
their own unique
strengths and their own unique qualities. And so comparing ourselves to other
people on cam is
just never going to make us feel good. However, connecting with other people,
even if it's to say
in the group, for example, I'm feeling a bit crap today or I'm not feeling good
about this or
whatever it is, there will be people there to support you. And it helps so much
just to have
a few words from somebody who can see you and who can empathize with you and
who supports you
can make such a huge difference. So I'm going to talk a little bit now about
coping with
difficult clients, because this is one thing that came out of the call that we
did,
is that some people, when they talked about confidence on cam or what not to
their confidence,
we're talking about coping with difficult clients. So I wanted to talk a bit
about this.
So confidence can be hugely enhanced by knowing that you cope well with
difficult
clients. And here's just a few practical steps to help with this. So we talked
about boundaries,
knowing your boundaries beforehand. And that also includes knowing how to
implement your boundaries.
So how you're going to adjust your behaviour if your boundaries are crossed as
we talked about earlier.
So separating yourself from your client's words, behaviours or judgments. So
this is really
important if you have a difficult client or somebody that's a bit triggering or
just not being very
nice. Hopefully this is rare. But to be able to separate yourself from the
client's words,
behaviours or judgments is so important. Their client, if they're saying
anything to you or about
you, which is negative, they're projecting something onto you. So it's not
about you. And of course,
as it says here, you can notice any triggers you may have around this.
And it's really good actually to know your own triggers because then you know
when something's
consistently coming up for you or you're noticing something or you're just
interpreting something,
it's great to know your own triggers. But also to understand that if somebody's
saying something
negative to you, there's a reason why they're doing that. And that's about them
and not about you.
Use spot lighting to regain control of your room or the conversation or give
yourself
permission to end a call or block the client. So of course, we always say, you
know, you're in
total control, you can end a call at any time, you can block someone at any
time. But spot lighting
is something that's really useful. So there's a book here, Unbound, A Woman's
Guide to Power.
I know that we quite often quote this when we're talking about stuff like this.
And I think
this concept comes from this book, which is spot lighting. So I'll try and give
an example of what
this looks like. So usually when you have a client that is triggering you, or
that's difficult for
you, or that's just being difficult, normally what they are doing is putting
the spotlight on you.
So this could be that it's not even a difficult client per se. It could be that
it's not that
somebody's not being nice to you. It's just that they're making you feel like
the power dynamic is
off. You know, you feel like powerless or helpless, or you don't know what to
say or do or whatever.
And usually this is because the client is spot lighting you. So they're saying
whatever language
they're using, it's about you. And they're expecting something from you in that
moment. And we kind of
can be like a rabbit in the headlights. We're like, Oh God, like what do I say
next? Or what do I do?
Like this person's making me feel a certain way. And I don't know. It's making
me think about myself
and feel insecure or not know what to say next. Well, spot lighting is about
noticing that you
feel like you're in the spotlight, that you've got that like rabbit in the
headlights feeling.
And rather than staying in that state, it is like consciously, supposed like
figuratively,
turning that spotlight back on the other person. So this this can work in like
everyday life,
but it's great for cam as well. So you notice that you're feeling like a rabbit
in the headlights,
the other person feels like they have all the control. They're saying they're
asking you a
question or they're saying a statement about you or they're expecting something
from you. And you
feel like you're in this in the spotlight. The most simple way to deal with a
client like that
is to ask a question. So it sounds super, super simple. But what you're aiming
for is
note that the spotlight is no longer going to be our cue. You're going to make
the spotlight
turn back onto them. So they might say something like, I'm trying to think of
an example, like,
they might say something like, what would you say? What do you do about this?
Or how do you do this?
Or like they say something to you, but it comes across in that very nice way
and you feel like
really on the spot. Or something you might say to them, it might sound like,
maybe like it's
interesting that you ask me that question. What makes you want to know? Or, you
know, it's like
when somebody somebody gives you a like misogynistic comment, they say that
they just say something
that's inappropriate to you and you just feel a bit like, oh, well, instead of
like feeling that
awkwardness and that and that feeling, it's just putting the question the
spotlight back onto that
person. So did that feel good to ask me that question? Or what response are you
hoping for
from that question? Or how does it make you feel to be asking me that question?
So rather than staying
with what's going on for you, coming back to curiosity, I'm turning the
spotlight back on the
person, because there's always something to be curious about. If somebody is
making you feel a
certain way, that is something to be curious about. And that's an opportunity
to put the spotlight
back on your client. So hopefully that made sense. I can talk a bit more about
that to anybody that
needs, you know, is interested in that or wants to know what the book is called
or there's lots
of other books and lots of other theories around that. And that's just one
small thing that I think
can be so helpful when you've got a difficult client, take a moment to notice
you feel like
that spotlighting, that you feel like a rabbit in the headlight, take a moment,
put the spotlight back on them, ask them about them, ask them about that
question they just asked
you, ask them, do they usually ask people that question? Or that I noticed the
tone in that
question, is that because of this, like to just be curious and calm and putting
the spotlight back
on them. And of course, taking a breath, there's never any rush. So take a
breath and just resetting
your nervous system, reach out to other people if needed. There are some lovely
like somatic body
based exercises you can do. I don't know if you've ever heard of EFT, emotional
freedom technique,
which is tapping your body in different spots to calm your nervous system. So
you can have a look
at YouTube that, but there's loads of really good like grounding like body
based exercises you can
do as well to cope with difficult clients. And yes, I think it's important to
say that if you're
feeling low confidence, if you're feeling anxious, a lack of confidence can
simply be a lack of
practice or experience. We all show up, you know, on day one coming, not
knowing what we're going to
say, do how this works. That's totally normal. It's totally normal to have
nerves and it's totally
normal to feel a bit anxious. And gaining knowledge and experience and self
trust with all the things
you talked about can really help. And there are so many courses, training calls
, so many resources
on the website that you can tap into. I mean, we've got five years worth of
content there
at your fingertips. So much of it is about confidence and so much of it is
about
gaining knowledge and experience and advice for camp. And so tapping into that
can be so
important, can be a game changer really when you're building your webcam
business.
And yeah, lastly, just to come back to this point, because I think it's such an
important one,
comparison is the thief of joy. We all know that saying, but I like the end of
that saying, which
is, and the tool of patriarchy. So we are conditioned to compare ourselves to
other people. It keeps us
powerless. It keeps us small. And we don't need to do that here in this
community. So be aware of
what you consume. Be aware of the people, the relationships you have around you
. Be aware of
the power dynamics that you're a part of, maybe in your work or wherever else.
And just allow yourself
some time and some space to step out of those and to step away from comparison
and into connection
with people. Because that's what really helps to build our confidence.
Yes, if there's anything you'd like to share, obviously we've already done this
call, but please
feel free to share any of your thoughts about the call, any of your thoughts
about yourself,
your own journey, any of your own tips, and please share them with us in their
WhatsApp.
We'd love to hear them.